Mashaan Alshammari

Riyadh, Saudi Arabia mashaan.awad@outlook.com

Last Updated: March 2024







I am a machine learning researcher, working on graph clustering and deep learning problems. Previously, I held academic positions in an Australian institute and a Saudi university. I designed CS material at masters and undergraduate levels.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Computer Science, The University of Sydney,

Thesis title: "Graph Filtering and Automatic Parameter Selection for Efficient Spectral Clustering."

Master of Science, Computer Science, King Fahd University of Petroleum and Minerals (KFUPM),

Thesis title: "Human In-Place Action Recognition using Combination of Kinect Data Streams."

Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, University of Hail,

2005—2010

SKILLS

Research & Development1st author in 13+ research papers, 60+ verified reviews on Web of Science.TechnicalPython and Java programming, Python's ML\DL libraries (pytorch, jax, flax, scikit-learn).Curriculum designDesigning CS courses according to Australian Qualifications Framework (AQF) and NCAAA.Social Media25+ stars on my Github, 4600+ views and 75+ likes on my YouTube educational videos.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

CURRICULUM DEVELOPMENT COLLABORATOR

Jul 2023 — Present Sydney, Australia

Sydney Polytechnic Institute

- Participated in curriculum development for a Master of Data Science and Bachelor of Computing.
- Designed the outline and planner documents for courses: Database Systems (U211), Cybersecurity and Information Assurance (U312), and Full-stack development (U322).

MACHINE LEARNING RESEARCHER

JUN 2022 — Present

Freelance

Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

- · Working on machine learning research with researchers from the University of Sydney and KFUPM.
- · Our research focuses on Graph Convolutional Network (GCN) and Unsupervised Domain Adaptation (UDA).
- Designed experiments using python ML libraries (scikit-learn, pytorch, seaborn, and others).

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR

JAN 2021 — JUN 2022

University of Hail

Hail, Saudi Arabia

- Participated in curriculum design and lecturing for multiple graduate and undergraduate computer science
- Adapted new teaching strategies to teach the following courses: data structures (ICS202), advanced database (ICS434), and machine learning for big data (CSAI510).

CURRICULUM DEVELOPMENT COLLABORATOR

SEP 2020 — MAR 2021

Sydney Polytechnic Institute

Sydney, Australia

- Participated in curriculum development for a Master of Data Science.
- Designed lecture slides, assignments, practical sessions, and exams for courses: Database Systems and Infrastructure (MDS604), Mathematics for data science (MDS602), and Artificial Intelligence and Innovation (MDS607).

SYSTEM ENGINEER AUG 2010 — MAY 2012

SABIC

Jubail, Saudi Arabia

- In charge of securing and maintaining the plant network components.
- · Upgraded obsolete network components during online operation.

INTERN

Saudi Aramco

Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

- · Completed cooperative training at EXPEC ARC as a member of Computational Modeling Team.
- Developed a GUI interface populating the simulator output, large text files, into a database.

Mashaan Alshammari

Last Updated: March 2024

Riyadh, Saudi Arabia mashaan.awad@outlook.com







SELECTED PROJECTS

My YouTube Channel

pytorch, jax, Jupyter Notebook

- I create videos explaining machine learning methods. The video starts by reading a paper or a book and ends with code.
- I cover topics like how a convolutional layer is implemented as matrix multiplication in pytorch.

VisionTransformer-MNIST

ViT, pytorch, Jupyter Notebook

- Implementation of the paper "An Image is Worth 16x16 Words: Transformers for Image Recognition at Scale", which was published by Google research.
- Vision transformers replaces CNNs as the preferred method for image classification.

Graph Convolutional Networks (GCNs)

GNNs, GCNs, pytorch, Jupyter Notebook

- Implementation of the paper "Semi-Supervised Classification with Graph Convolutional Networks", which was published in ICLR 2017.
- Graph Convolutional Networks (GCNs) perform node classification in graphs.

ADDA

GANs, pytorch, Jupyter Notebook

- Implementation of the paper "Adversarial Discriminative Domain Adaptation", which was published in CVPR 2017.
- ADDA uses GANs to perform unsupervised domain adaptation (UDA).

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "*Graph Construction using Principal Axis Trees for Simple Graph Convolution.*", **arXiv**:2302.12000, 2023.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "*Random projection forest initialization for graph convolutional networks*.", **MethodsX**, 2023.
- Mashaan Alshammari, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Random projection tree similarity metric for SpectralNet.", Array, 2023.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "The Effect of Points Dispersion on the k-nn Search in Random Projection Forests.", **IEEE Access**, 2022.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, John Stavrakakis, Masahiro Takatsuka: "A Parameter-Free Graph Reduction for Spectral Clustering and Spectralnet.", **Array**, 2022.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, John Stavrakakis, Masahiro Takatsuka: "*Refining a k-nearest neighbor graph for a computationally efficient spectral clustering*.", **Pattern Recognition**, 2021.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, Masahiro Takatsuka: "*Approximate spectral clustering density-based similarity for noisy datasets*.", **Pattern Recognition Letters**, 2019.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, Masahiro Takatsuka: "*Approximate spectral clustering with eigenvector selection and self-tuned k.*", **Pattern Recognition Letters**, 2019.

SELECTED ACTIVITIES

Journal Reviewer

- Pattern Recognition Journal
- · Information Sciences Journal
- · Knowledge-Based Systems Journal

Conference Organization

- <u>Program committee</u>, 30th International Conference on Neural Information Processing (ICONIP2023), Changsha, China, November 20-23, 2023.
- <u>Technical Program Committee</u>, 7th International Conference on Data Science and Machine Learning Applications (CDMA2022), Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, March 1-3, 2022.